<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>FPath Tutorial</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Pierre-Charles</firstname>
      <surname>David</surname>
      <email>pcdavid@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1 id="introduction">
    <title>What is FPath?</title>

    <para>FPath is a query language for software architectures, and especially
    Fractal-based architectures (this document will only consider Fractal as a
    target model). On other words, it is a Domain Specific Language (DSL) which
    make it easy to navigate inside component systems built using Fractal, and
    to find elements of the architecture (e.g. components) which match some
    criterion.</para>

    <para>The Fractal component model makes this kind of querying possible thanks to
    its extensive support for reflection (and in particular introspection in
    this case). However, because of the way the model is defined (as a
    language-independent, minimalist API), it is not very easy to use: typically
    you need to write several dozens of lines of Java even for conceptually
    simple queries, and the result is usually not very readable. Consider the
    following example program, in Java, which finds the attribute named
    <literal>header</literal> in the <quote>Hello World</quote>s example Fractal
    application, and returns its value:</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[public Object getHeaderValue(Component root) {
    try {
        Object[] children = Fractal.getContentController(root).getFcSubComponents();
        for (Object rawChild : children) {
            Component kid = (Component) rawChild;
            String name = "";
            try {
                name = Fractal.getNameController(kid).getFcName();
            } catch (NoSuchInterfaceException nsie) {
                continue;
            }
            if (name.equals("client")) {
                try {
                    Interface itf = (Interface) Fractal.getBindingController(kid).lookupFc("s");
                    if (itf == null) {
                        return null;
                    }
                    Component server = itf.getFcItfOwner();
                    AttributeController ac = Fractal.getAttributeController(server);
                    Class klass = ac.getClass();
                    try {
                        Method meth = null;
                        try {
                            meth = klass.getMethod("getHeader", null);
                        } catch (NoSuchMethodException nime) {
                            return null;
                        }
                        try {
                            return meth.invoke(ac, null);
                        } catch (Exception e) {
                            return null;
                        }
                    } catch (Exception e) {
                        return null;
                    }
                } catch (NoSuchInterfaceException nsie) {
                    return null;
                }
            }
        }
        return null;
    } catch (Exception _) {
        return null;
    }
}]]></programlisting>

    <para>Contrast these 45 lines of Java with the equivalent query in FPath:</para>

    <programlisting>value($root/client/interface::s/binding::*/@header)</programlisting>

    <para>The FPath syntax is roughly inspired by the XPath query language for
    XML documents (hence the name). If you are familiar with XPath, the example
    query above should not be too difficult to understand. Otherwise, don't
    worry! This document will explain everything you need to know to read FPath
    queries, and write your own.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="setup">
    <title>Installing the required components for the tutorial</title>

    <sect2 id="obtaining">
      <title>Installing FPath</title>

      <para>FPath is implemented as part of the FScript language and project, itself
      hosted in <ulink url="http://fractal.objectweb.org/">the Fractal top-level project
      on OW2</ulink>.</para>

      <para>FPath can be used from Java applications using a simple API, but in this
      tutorial we will use the console application. It provides an easy-to-use interactive
      shell to evaluate FPath queries. To actually follow this tutorial, you must install
      both FScript itself and the interactive console application. See the <ulink
      url="installing.html">installation instructions</ulink> on the dedicated
      page.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="comanche">
      <title>Getting the example application</title>

      <para>In order to illustrate FPath, we need a target Fractal application to
      introspect and query. In this tutorial, we will use Comanche, the canonical example
      Fractal application. Comanche is a minimalist HTTP server built by Éric Bruneton as
      an example of how to create Fractal applications.</para>

      <para>You can get a ready-to use JAR file with Comanche here: <ulink
      url="comanche.jar">comanche.jar</ulink>. This version is slightly modified from the
      standard one in the Fractal repository, so it is recommended you use this JAR if you
      want to get the exact same results as shown in this document.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="comanche-architecture"/> shows the architecture of the Comanche
      application. It consists in two main components, the <emphasis>Frontend</emphasis>
      and the <emphasis>Backend</emphasis>, wrapped in a top-level composite. The frontend
      listens on a socket for incoming requests (<emphasis>Receiver</emphasis>) and sends
      these requests to the back-end for processing, according to the policy defined in
      the <emphasis>Scheduler</emphasis> component. The backend parses the requests it
      receives (<emphasis>Analyzer</emphasis>), logs it (<emphasis>Logger</emphasis>) and
      sends it to the <emphasis>Handler</emphasis> component which actually computes the
      response. Inside the <emphasis>Handler</emphasis>, a <emphasis>Dispatcher</emphasis>
      successively sends the request to all the actual handler components it is connected
      to (e.g. <emphasis>FileHandler</emphasis>), until one of them can handle the
      request.</para>

      <figure id="comanche-architecture">
        <title>The architecture of the Comanche HTTP server.</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/comanche.png" align="center"/>
      </figure>

      <note>
        <para>As you'll see in the following, the actual implementation of Comanche uses
        different (much shorter) names for the components. For example, the
        <emphasis>Dispatcher</emphasis> component in the figure is actually named
        <literal>rd</literal> in the implementation (short for <quote>request
        dispatcher</quote>).</para>
      </note>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="setup">
    <title>Setting up the example application</title>

    <para>In this first section, we will instantiate an example Fractal application inside
    the interactive console, so that we have something to query for the rest of the
    tutorial.</para>

    <sect2 id="launch">
      <title>Launching the interactive console</title>

      <para>In order to issue FPath queries and see their results, we will use the
      interactive console application provided in the FScript project. The console is
      actually just a normal client application which uses the Java APIs provided by
      FScript, the same way your applications can. (If your goal is to use FPath and/or
      FScript from your Java programs, first read this tutorial and <ulink
      url="tutorial-fscript.xml">the FScript one</ulink>, and then go to <ulink
      url="tutorial-apis.html">the Java APIs tutorial</ulink>.)</para>

      <para>To start the console application, go to the directory where the two JARs you
      downloaded earlier are (<literal>fscript-full.jar</literal> and
      <literal>comanche.jar</literal>), and the issue the following command:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>%</prompt> <userinput>java -jar fscript-full.jar</userinput>
<computeroutput>FScript console.

Useful commands:
- type ':help' for a list of available commands
- type ':help &lt;cmd&gt;' for detailed help on a specific command
- type ':quit' to exit

<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt></computeroutput></screen>

      <para>You should be greeted by the FScript console's prompt. As you can see from the
      welcome message, the console understands a few commands like
      <literal>:help</literal> and <literal>:quit</literal>. These are
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> part of the FPath language, but special commands to control
      the console application itself. We'll explain a few of these in this tutorial, but
      you can enter <literal>:help</literal> at the prompt to get a complete list.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="new-comanche">
      <title>Creating the example application</title>

      <para>Before we can create an instance of Comanche to play with, we need to add the
      JAR to the console's classpath. Remember that when we started the console, we
      launched the <literal>fscript-full.jar</literal> JAR directly, with nothing else in
      the classpath. You can add a new entry to the console's classpath using the
      <literal>:classpath_add</literal> console command:</para>

      <screen><prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>:classpath_add file:///full/path/to/comanche.jar</userinput>
<computeroutput>Classpath updated.</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>The argument passed to the command can be any URL which Java understands. For
      local files, use a <literal>file://</literal> URL.</para>

      <para>Now that all the required code and ADL definitions are available, we can
      create an instance of Comanche:</para>

      <screen><prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>c = adl-new('comanche.Comanche');</userinput>
<computeroutput>=> #&lt;component: comanche.Comanche&gt;</computeroutput>
<computeroutput>Success (took 524 ms).</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>This command invokes the <literal>adl-new()</literal> primitive operation with
      the name of the Fractal ADL component definition to instantiate, and stores the
      result in a variable named <literal>c</literal>. Note that this line is actually not
      an FPath expression, but an FScript statement. The difference is that FPath
      expressions can not have any side-effect: they can't modify the target architecture
      (only introspect them), and they can't even bind new variables. As we need to create
      a Comanche instance to have something to introspect, we need to use FScript (a
      super-set of FPath) to begin. Most of the rest of this tutorial is pure FPath, but
      we'll sometimes use FScript statements to define variables from the result of FPath
      queries.</para>

      <para>Once it has executed the statement above, creating a new instance of Comanche,
      the console tells us how must time it took, and prints the value of the statement.
      In this case, the value is <literal>#&lt;component: comanche.Comanche&gt;</literal>,
      which denotes a single <emphasis>component node</emphasis> named
      <literal>comanche.Comanche</literal>. FPath uses a generic notion of
      <emphasis>node</emphasis> to represent all the elements in a software architecture.
      Different architectural models may define different kinds of nodes, depending on the
      concepts they use. For example in the case of Fractal, there are three kinds of
      nodes: <emphasis>component</emphasis> nodes (representing the Fractal components
      themselves), <emphasis>interface</emphasis> nodes (their interfaces, be they
      internal or external, client or server, etc.), and <emphasis>attribute</emphasis>
      nodes (representing the configuration attributes defined by the components'
      <literal>attribute-controller</literal>).</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="basics">
    <title>FPath basics: nodes, properties and simple navigation</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Component Nodes</title>

      <para>We now have everything set up correctly to actually issue FPath queries to
      introspect Comanche.</para>

      <para>The first thing we can try is to look a the variable we have just defined
      above. To get the value of a variable, simply prefix its name with a dollar sign
      (<literal>$</literal>): </para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; #&lt;component: comanche.Comanche&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>This is a node which represents the top-level component of the Comanche
      application. Each kind of node in FPath defined a set of named properties, which
      have primitive values: strings, numbers, booleans, etc. In the case of Fractal, the
      component nodes have two properties: a <emphasis>name</emphasis>, and a
      <emphasis>state</emphasis>. We can get the values of these properties by using the
      function of the same name:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>name($c)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; "comanche.Comanche"</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>state($c)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; "STOPPED"</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>The results correspond to what you would get from Fractal's
      <literal>NameController#getFcName()</literal> and
      <literal>LifeCycleController#getFcState()</literal> methods.</para>

      <para>Let's now look at the content of this component:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/child::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 2 element(s):
#&lt;component: be&gt;   #&lt;component: fe&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>The expression <literal>$c/child::*</literal> is our first example of an
      actual <emphasis>path expression</emphasis>. It selects all the (direct) children of
      component <literal>$c</literal>, and returns them in a node-set. In this case, the
      result is a set of two components (more precisely two nodes representing the
      components) named <literal>fe</literal> and <literal>be</literal>. These correspond
      to the <emphasis>Frontend</emphasis> (<literal>fe</literal>) and
      <emphasis>Backend</emphasis> (<literal>be</literal>) components, which are indeed
      the two direct sub-components of the Comanche top-level (see <xref
      linkend="comanche-architecture"/>).</para>

      <para>A path expression is made of a sequence of <emphasis>steps</emphasis>,
      separated by slashes (<literal>/</literal>). Here there are only two
      (<literal>$c</literal> and <literal>child::*</literal>), but we can chain more to
      extend the query. For example, to get the children's children:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/child::*/child::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 5 element(s):
#&lt;component: l&gt;    #&lt;component: ra&gt;   #&lt;component: rh&gt;
#&lt;component: rr&gt;   #&lt;component: s></computeroutput></screen>

      <para>The result is a set of 5 components, containing the direct children of both
      the frontend and the backend.</para>

      <para>The first step in a path is the starting point of the query, and must evaluate
      to a node or set of nodes. Here <literal>$c</literal> evaluates to the top-level
      Comanche component. The next steps are then evaluated in sequence, taking as input
      the result of the previous step, and producing a set of nodes. The result of the
      whole query is the result of the last step.</para>

      <para>To understand how the last query works, you can read it like this: <quote>From
      the node (or node-set) in <literal>$c</literal>, first select all its children
      (<literal>fe</literal> and <literal>be</literal>). For each element of this
      intermediary result, select all of <emphasis>their</emphasis> children, put them
      together (both <literal>fe</literal>'s and <literal>be</literal>'s children) in a
      set, and return the result.</quote></para>

      <para>The star in <literal>child::*</literal> means: <quote>select
      <emphasis>all</emphasis> the children</quote>. If you are only interested by a
      particular child, you can specify its name in place of the star. For example:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/child::fe/child::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 2 element(s):
#&lt;component: rr&gt; #&lt;component: s&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>Here the first step of the path selected only the frontend instead of both the
      frontend and backend. The final results thus contains only the frontend's
      children.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Interface Nodes</title>

      <para>Until now, we've only seen components, but of course a Fractal architecture
      contains other interesting elements. FPath defines three kinds of nodes to model
      Fractal architectures: <emphasis>component</emphasis>, which we've seen,
      <emphasis>interfaces</emphasis>, and <emphasis>attributes</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>If instead of selecting the sub-components of <literal>$c</literal> we want to
      see its external interfaces, we can use the following query:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/interface::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 7 element(s):
#&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.binding-controller&gt;   #&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.component&gt;
#&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.content-controller&gt;   #&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.lifecycle-controller&gt;
#&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.name-controller&gt;      #&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.r&gt;
#&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.super-controller&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>Here we see that the result is still a set of nodes, but this time the nodes
      represents the component's (external) interfaces. As before, we can select a
      specific interface, for example the <literal>r</literal> interface, by its name.
      We'll store it in a new variable so we can reference it later:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>r = $c/interface::r;</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.r&gt;
Success (took 2 ms).</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>Component nodes had only two properties (<literal>name()</literal> and
      <literal>state()</literal>. Interface nodes have six of them, which give access to
      everything you may want to know about an interface. These correspond to all the
      properties defined in both Fractal <literal>Interface</literal> and
      <literal>InterfaceType</literal> interfaces. Here are their value for the interface
      <literal>$r</literal>:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>name($r)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; "r"</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>internal($r)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; false</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>signature($r)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; "java.lang.Runnable"</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>collection($r)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; false</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>optional($r)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; false</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>client($r)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; false</computeroutput></screen>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Attribute Nodes</title>

      <para>The third and final kind of node used in FPath represents configuration
      attributes, as defined by the components' <literal>attribute-controller</literal>
      interface. Let's select one and see what properties it has:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>p = $c/child::fe/child::s/attribute::poolSize;</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;attribute: s.poolSize&gt;
Success (took 2 ms).</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>Here we select (and store in a new variable <literal>$p</literal>) the
      attribute named <literal>poolSize</literal> from the <emphasis>Scheduler</emphasis>
      component (simply named <literal>s</literal> in the implementation), which is itself
      a child of the frontend <literal>fe</literal>. Its properties are the
      following:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>name($p)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; "poolSize"</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>type($p)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; "int"</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>value($p)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; 0</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>readable($p)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; true</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>writable($p)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; true</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>We've now seen seen all the kinds of nodes available in FPath, and introduced
      the basics of navigation. The next section will explain more of the underlying
      principles, and introduce more sophisticated ways to navigate inside Fractal
      architectures.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="axes">
    <title>Navigation axes</title>

    <para>In the previous section, we've seen that FPath models software architectures
    using <emphasis>nodes</emphasis> to represent the elements of interest (components,
    interfaces and attributes in the case of Fractal). By themselves, nodes can only model
    individual elements, and do not give us any information on the actual structure of the
    system. To represent the structure, FPath connects the nodes using directed arcs. The
    result is that, from FPath's point of view, a software architecture is a directed
    graph. The vertices of this graph are the nodes we've already seen, and the edges are
    labelled arcs between these nodes, which represent their relationships.</para>

    <para>The different kinds of relationships which can exist between nodes are called
    <emphasis>axes</emphasis>, and are the basic mechanism for navigation in FPath. We've
    actually already met three axes in the previous section: <literal>child</literal>,
    <literal>interface</literal> and <literal>attribute</literal>:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><literal>child</literal> labels arcs which connect composite nodes
      to the nodes representing their direct sub-component</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><literal>interface</literal> labels arcs which connect component
      nodes to the nodes representing its external interfaces</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><literal>attribute</literal> labels arcs which connect component
      nodes to the nodes representing its configuration attributes</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>With this information, we can now understand in more details what the queries
    from the previous section do. When we write <literal>$c/child::*</literal>, it
    actually means: <quote>From the node(s) in variable <literal>$c</literal>, traverse
    all the arcs in the graph labelled <literal>child</literal>, and return the nodes at
    the other end.</quote> Each step in a path <quote>walks</quote> along the
    corresponding axis in the graph, returning the destination nodes at the other end of
    the arcs.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Other primitive axes</title>

      <para>FPath provides several other axes to navigate in Fractal architecture. The
      so-called <emphasis>primitive</emphasis> axes presented in this section correspond
      to relationships directly available in Fractal. In addition to the
      <literal>child</literal>, <literal>interface</literal> and
      <literal>attribute</literal> axes we've already seen, these are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <literal>parent</literal>axis is the inverse of
          <literal>child</literal>, and connects a component node to its direct parents.
          For example:</para>

          <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>fe = $c/child::fe;</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt;  a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;component: fe&gt;
Success (took 1 ms).</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$fe/parent::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt;  a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;component: comanche.Comanche&gt;
Success (took 1 ms).</computeroutput></screen>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <literal>internal-interface</literal> axis is the equivalent of the
          <literal>interface</literal> axis, but for internal interfaces instead of
          external ones:</para>

          <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/internal-interface::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.r&gt;</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$fe/child::s/internal-interface::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 0 element(s):</computeroutput></screen>

          <para>As can be seen from the second query above, using this axis on a primitive
          component (which can not have internal interfaces) is not an error, but simply
          returns an empty result.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <literal>component</literal> is a little special: it connects
          interfaces and attributes nodes to their owner component, and component nodes to
          themselves. Basically, from any kind of node, <literal>component::*</literal>
          can be used to go back to a well known place:</para>

          <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/component::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;component: comanche.Comanche&gt;</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/interface::*/component::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;component: comanche.Comanche&gt;</computeroutput>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/child::fe/child::s/attribute::poolSize/component::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;component: s&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Finally, the <literal>binding</literal> axis connects a node representing
          a client interface to the node representing the server interface it is bound to,
          is any. It is almost always used in the form <literal>binding::*</literal>. For
          example:</para>

          <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/internal-interface::r/binding::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;interface: fe.r&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

          <para>This tells us that the interface named <literal>r</literal> of the
          top-level Comanche component is actually provided internally by the (server)
          interface of the same name of the frontend. Similarly:</para>

          <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/child::be/child::ra/interface::rh/binding::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;interface: rh.rh&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

          <para>tells us that the request analyzer component (<literal>ra</literal>) is
          bound to the request handler (<literal>rh</literal>) through an interface called
          <literal>rh</literal> (on both sides).</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Derived axes</title>

      <para>In addition to the primitive axes described in the previous section, FPath
      provides other axes which are <emphasis>derived</emphasis> from these, and greatly
      improve the power of FPath as a query language.</para>

      <para>First, the <literal>child</literal> and <literal>parent</literal> axes have
      transitive versions respectively called <literal>descendant</literal> and
      <literal>ancestor</literal>. Whereas <literal>child</literal> (resp.
      <literal>parent</literal>) only gives access to the <emphasis>direct</emphasis>
      sub-components (resp. super-components), the transitive version
      <literal>descendant</literal> (resp. <literal>ancestor</literal>) gives access to
      <emphasis>all</emphasis> the sub-components (resp. super-components),
      recursively.</para>

      <para>This is very useful when you want to find a component by name, but do not know
      exactly where it is in the architecture. For example, to find the logger component
      <literal>l</literal> in Comanche:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/descendant::l</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;component: l&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>and all its ancestors:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/descendant::l/ancestor::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 2 element(s):
#&lt;component: be&gt; #&lt;component: comanche.Comanche&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>These two axes also exist in <emphasis>reflective and transitive</emphasis>
      versions, named <literal>descendant-or-self</literal> and
      <literal>ancestor-or-self</literal>. The difference is that the starting nodes are
      also included in the result. <literal>descendant-or-self</literal> is particularly
      useful to select <emphasis>all</emphasis> the components in an architecture in
      one step:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/descendant-or-self::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 11 element(s):
#&lt;component: be&gt;  #&lt;component: comanche.Comanche&gt; #&lt;component: erh&gt; #&lt;component: fe&gt;
#&lt;component: frh&gt; #&lt;component: l&gt;                 #&lt;component: ra&gt;  #&lt;component: rd&gt;
#&lt;component: rh&gt;  #&lt;component: rr&gt;                #&lt;component: s&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>One final derived axis is <literal>sibling</literal>: it connects a component
      node to all the other components in the architecture which share at least one parent
      with it (including itself).</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/child::fe/sibling::*</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 2 element(s):
#&lt;component: be&gt;  #&lt;component: fe&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="predicates">
    <title>Filtering predicates</title>

    <para>Until now, we've been using axes in a very coarse-grained way. We can either
    select an element by name (as in <literal>child::fe</literal>) or all the elements at
    the end of an axis (as in <literal>child::*</literal>). FPath supports a mechanism of
    <emphasis>filtering predicates</emphasis> which allow for much more powerful queries.
    At each step in a path, we can add one or several predicate expressions, put between
    brackets, which can filter candidate nodes according to their properties.</para>

    <para>For example, <literal>$c/child::*[name(.) == 'fe']</literal> is equivalent to
    <literal>$c/child::fe</literal>. <literal>$c/child::*</literal> by itself would select
    all the sub-components of <literal>$c</literal>, but the filter expression retains
    only the one(s) whose name is <literal>fe</literal>.</para>

    <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/child::*[name(.) == 'fe']</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 1 element(s):
#&lt;component: fe&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

    <para>Inside the brackets, the dot (<literal>.</literal>) represents the implicit
    argument to the predicate, i.e. the candidate node being tested. The predicate
    expression is evaluated for each candidate node, and if the result is true, the node
    is selected to be part of the result; otherwise it is removed from the
    result-set.</para>

    <para>With this mechanism, we can for select all the (external)
    <emphasis>client</emphasis> interfaces from any component in the architecture:</para>

    <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/descendant-or-self::*/interface::*[client(.)]</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 8 element(s):
#&lt;interface: fe.rh&gt;   #&lt;interface: ra.l&gt;    #&lt;interface: ra.rh&gt;   #&lt;interface: rd.h0&gt;   #&lt;interface: rd.h1&gt;   #&lt;interface: rd.h&gt;
#&lt;interface: rr.rh&gt;   #&lt;interface: rr.s&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

    <para>or maybe select interfaces according to their signature:</para>

    <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/descendant-or-self::*/interface::*[signature(.) == "java.lang.Runnable"]</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 3 element(s):
#&lt;interface: comanche.Comanche.r&gt;   #&lt;interface: fe.r&gt;   #&lt;interface: rr.r&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

    <para>The expression used as a predicate can be any FPath expression, including a
    path. Let's say we want to find the components which provide configuration attributes:</para>

    <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/descendant-or-self::*[./attribute::*]</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; a node-set with 2 element(s):
#&lt;component: frh&gt;   #&lt;component: s&gt;</computeroutput></screen>

    <para>The expression in the brackets is a relative path, which starts with the
    candidate node to test (<literal>.</literal>). It returns a set of attributes nodes,
    which will be empty if the starting node does not have any attribute. When used in a
    predicate, a node-set is considered true if and only if it is not-empty, so the end
    result is that only the components which have at least one attribute are selected by
    the predicate.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sets">
    <title>Using set operations</title>

    <para>FPath also supports three standard set operations to combine the results of
    queries:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To take the <emphasis>union</emphasis> of the node-sets, you can use the
        <quote>pipe</quote> operator <literal>|</literal>, or the
        <literal>union()</literal> function (they are equivalent).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To take the <emphasis>intersection</emphasis> of the node-sets, you can use
        the <literal>&amp;</literal> operator, or the equivalent
        <literal>intersection()</literal> function.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Finally, to take the <emphasis>difference</emphasis> of the node-sets, you
        can use the <quote>backslash</quote> operator <literal>\</literal>, or the
        equivalent <literal>difference()</literal> function.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For example, to check that <literal>descendant-or-self</literal> is actually the
    reflective version of <literal>descendant</literal>:</para>

    <screen>
<prompt>FScript&gt;</prompt> <userinput>$c/descendant-or-self::* == ($c/descendant::* | $c)</userinput>
<computeroutput>=&gt; true</computeroutput></screen>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="shortcuts">
    <title>Shortcut notation</title>

    <para>FPath 2.0 now supports a few shortcut notations for the most commonly used axes.
    We have not used them in this tutorial to show the language mechanisms more
    explicitly, but they make complex queries much easier to write and to read:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <literal>child</literal> axis is the default when none is specified, so
        <literal>$c/child::fe/child::*</literal> can be shortened to
        <literal>$c/fe/*</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <literal>attribute</literal> axis can be shortened to
        <literal>@</literal>, so
        <literal>$c/child::fe/child::s/attribute::poolSize</literal> can be written more
        simply <literal>$c/fe/s/@poolSize</literal> (this also works with
        <literal>@*</literal>).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <literal>parent</literal> axis can be shortened to
        <literal>..</literal>, but only when used in the form
        <literal>parent::*</literal>, i.e. <literal>$fe/../interface::r</literal> instead
        of <literal>$fe/parent::*/interface::r</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Finally, the <literal>descendant-or-self</literal> axis can be shortened to
        <literal>/</literal>, giving <literal>//</literal> as a separator for steps:
        <literal>$c//s</literal> instead of <literal>$c/descendant-or-self::s</literal>,
        and even <literal>$c//*[./@*]</literal> instead of
        <literal>$c/descendant-or-self::*[./attribute::*]</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

</article>
